Rhiannon: Legislation and guidance and
the processes connected with them, are
there to protect and support the rights
of all children and young people and
their families, and also provide support
to those who work with children and
young people with mental health issues.
Leah: Whether in the home, at school
or in a mental health setting, a child
or young person should never be treated
in a way that is inhumane or degrading.
They should always be protected
from abuse or neglect that can
cause mental or physical harm.
Rhiannon: The family and by
extension, family life, should
also be respected at all times.
For example, sending a child or young
person to another part of the country
for residential care and support makes it
harder for family visits and maintaining
those important relationships which
can be distressing for all concerned.
Leah: Wherever possible a young person
should be consulted about their care
and be involved in the decision making.
If the child is deemed not legally
competent, consent should be obtained
from someone with parental responsibility,
unless in the case of an emergency.
Rhiannon: Parental responsibility
should be involved in all
important decision making in
relation to a child, for example:
- where the child goes to school,
- appointing a guardian in the
event of the loss of a parent,
- consenting to medical treatment
- and accessing a child’s medical records.
Leah: This is also the case for legal
matters, and religious or cultural
issues until the child reaches an
age to make their own decisions.
Let’s now look at how data
is used and protected.
Rhiannon: Any data held on children
and young adults comes under the
'data protection principles' and
that information must be used
fairly, lawfully and transparently.
It should always be up to date, relevant
and limited to only what is necessary.
Leah: Any information no longer needed,
should be then destroyed securely.
For example, childcare providers and
even child minders need to comply with
data protection for every child in their
care, even if that is for a limited time.
Rhiannon: With further advances in
digital footprints, there is now
stronger legal protection for online
identification markers, location data,
genetic information, biometrics and
more, and there are separate safeguards
for personal data which relate to
criminal convictions and offences.
Leah: The Data Protection Act, means
an individual has the right to know
what information the government and
other organisations store about them,
including, the right to be informed
about how it is being used, the ability
to have access to it and have it
corrected or erased when appropriate.
Rhiannon: Children especially, require
specific protection regarding their
data as they may not be fully aware of
the risks or consequences of processing
personal data or their rights.
Leah: With so much online communication,
children and young people are constantly
putting their data in the public
domain by signing up to the various
forms of social media and are not
always aware of the consequences.
Rhiannon: Adults with parental
responsibility should endeavour
to monitor that data is being used
correctly, whist still respecting the
rights of the child or young person.
Leah: We must remember legislation
and guidance is there to protect
and should be used accordingly.